<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>davidmaas</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on davidmaas</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:29:21 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Does the Single Source of Truth Exist?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/data-ssot/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:29:21 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/data-ssot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Single Source of Truth”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Few phrases in data management sound as definitive, and few are as misunderstood.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;For decades, it’s been the rallying cry of analytics and IT teams: one place where data is clean, consistent, and universally trusted.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But after countless data warehouses, data lakes, and governance initiatives, many organizations still struggle with conflicting numbers and fragmented definitions.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;So it’s worth asking: &lt;strong&gt;does the single source of truth actually exist?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Datavault Training | with datavaut4dbt on DuckDB</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/datavault4dbtonduckdb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 18:29:21 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/datavault4dbtonduckdb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, chances are you know &lt;a href=&#34;https://getdbt.com&#34;&gt;dbt&lt;/a&gt;. You probably also heard about Data Vault data modeling. In this post, I will show you how to build a Data Vault 2.0 model using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/davidraoulmaas/datavault4dbtonduckdb&#34;&gt;datavault4dbt - on DuckDB&lt;/a&gt;, my DuckDB adaption of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ScalefreeCOM/datavault4dbt&#34;&gt;Scalefrees datavault4dbt package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data Vault modeling has a bit of an entry barrier, because its concept is a bit more complex in the beginning. As it is usually used in business datawarehouses, you normally learn about it in business context and in paid trainings where you can also obtain official certifications. Free and easily accessible resources are rare.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Should the Data Organization Sit in IT?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/data-org/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 18:29:21 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/data-org/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Few questions in data leadership spark as much debate as this one:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Should the data organization sit in IT, or should it stand on its own?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At first glance, it sounds like an org-chart detail. In reality, it defines how your company thinks about data: as &lt;em&gt;infrastructure&lt;/em&gt; or as &lt;em&gt;a product&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen both setups and both can work.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;But the placement of the data team deeply shapes its culture, priorities, and even its speed.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;And while many companies instinctively tuck data under IT, that’s often more out of legacy convenience than strategic clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Architecture and the Real Total Cost of Ownership: Why “Make or Buy” Is Harder Than It Looks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/tco/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 16:29:21 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/tco/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every leadership team faces the same strategic dilemma sooner or later:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Should we build our own data stack, or should we buy into managed solutions?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On paper, the choice seems straightforward. “Building” gives you control and flexibility; “buying” gives you speed and convenience. In reality, the trade-offs run much deeper, especially when you look through the lens of &lt;strong&gt;Total Cost of Ownership (TCO)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, I’ve seen and have been part of teams starting with a DIY approach. State-of-the-art, terraform, containers, Airflow, dbt core, the works. It feels empowering: you control the stack, optimize for cost, and get to build something elegant and custom.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;But as months pass, the picture changes. What starts as an engineering playground quickly becomes a maintenance treadmill.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution of Data Architecture</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/data-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 13:29:21 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/data-evolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been around data long enough, you’ve probably seen this movie before.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;First, we fell in love with &lt;em&gt;no-/low-code ETL tools&lt;/em&gt; like SSIS, Matillion or Alteryx. Drag-and-drop nodes, colorful workflows, and a promise that “anyone can build data pipelines.”&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Then came the backlash: engineers wanted code, reproducibility, and control. Suddenly, everything had to be &lt;em&gt;in Terraform, Dockerized, and YAML-defined&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And now?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;We’re swinging back again, toward SaaS-first, declarative, and low-code data platforms.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Only this time, it’s not because we want simplicity. It’s because &lt;strong&gt;complexity finally became too expensive&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
